

■ ek8093@rit.edu | 🕯 emilykuang.github.io | 🞧 emilykuang | 🛅 emilykuang6

At the forefront of **Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Artificial Intelligence (AI), and User Experience (UX),** my research focuses on designing and evaluating human-AI collaborative tools for improved usability and UX analysis. Honored with the 2023 **Google PhD Fellowship in HCI**, my work not only advances technology but also champions accessibility, focusing on inclusive computing education and assistive technology for diverse user groups. This CV unfolds my journey of blending research with a commitment to inclusive, user-centered technology development.

# **Education**

## **Rochester Institute of Technology**

New York, United States

PhD in Computing and Information Sciences

Aug 2020 - present

- Advised by Dr. Kristen Shinohara and Dr. Mingming Fan
- Participating in the AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (NRT) Program

University of Waterloo Ontario, Canada

BASC IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

Sept 2015 - Apr 2020

- · Capstone advised by Dr. John Zelek
- · Graduated on Dean's Honour List

# **Experience**

# **Rochester Institute of Technology**

Rochester, NY, US

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug 2020 - present

- Conduct HCI research on the human-centered design of AI-powered technologies, focusing on visual analytic tools and conversational assistants to support UX analysis
- Design, conduct, and analyze research studies employing a variety of methods including interviews, surveys, design probes, usability studies, and quantitative experiments
- Author technical papers for publication and develop dissemination plans

Meta, Reality Labs

Seattle, WA, USA

Seattle, WA, USA

UX RESEARCH INTERN

May 2023 - Aug 2023

- · Designed and led a 20-participant interview study on VR headset user experiences, efficiently collaborating with research vendors
- Actively contributed to project brainstorming workshops and internal product demos
- Effectively communicated findings to diverse product stakeholders, promoting a comprehensive understanding of user perspectives and needs

Meta, Reality Labs

Burlingame, CA, US

UX RESEARCH INTERN

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- · Conducted literature reviews and authored reports on first-hand experiences to inform the design of Ray-ban | Meta smartglasses
- Designed and conducted a user study with 30 participants to investigate audio performance
- Presented results to >100 product stakeholders including researchers, engineers, and cross-functional partners; recommendations led to changes in product design

#### **Uncharted Software Inc., ASKE-E Team**

Toronto, ON, CA

RESEARCH INTERN

May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Worked on the DARPA Automating Scientific Knowledge Extraction (ASKE) program
- Designed wireframes and implemented new features in the human-machine interface (HMI) of a visual analytics system for multi-scale graph analysis and knowledge discovery

#### Huawei Technologies Canada, Human-Machine Interaction (HMI) Lab

Markham, ON, CA

RESEARCH ENGINEER

Jan - Aug 2019, May - Aug 2020

- Trained machine learning models for gesture recognition using Tensorflow
- Designed and conducted user experiments to explore novel interaction techniques on large screens using mid-air gesture input; presented at the Huawei Developer Conference 2019

# University of Waterloo, Vision and Image Processing (VIP) Lab

Waterloo, ON, CA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2016 - Apr 2018

- Designed and 3D-printed a lens-free microscope and a smartphone spectrometer
- · Conducted testing with biological specimens to achieve optical resolution in the nm range

# Publications \_\_\_\_\_

#### PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

[1] Bridging the Literacy Gap for Adults: Understanding How Streamers Teach Adult Literacy on Livestreaming Platforms

SHIHAN FU, JIANHAO CHEN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2024. (In press)

[2] Designing Unobtrusive Modulated Electrotactile Feedback on Fingertip Edge to Assist Blind and Low Vision (BLV) People in Comprehending Charts

CHUTIAN JIANG, YINAN FAN, JUNAN XIE, EMILY KUANG, KAIHAO ZHANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2024. (In press)

[3] Exploring the Opportunity of Augmented Reality (AR) in Supporting Older Adults Explore and Learn Smartphone Applications

XIAOFU JIN, WAI TONG, XIAOYING WEI, XIAN WANG, EMILY KUANG, XIAOYU MO, HUAMIN QU, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2024. (In press)

[4] Mapping Accessibility Assignments into Core Computer Science Topics: An Empirical Study with Interviews and Surveys of Instructors and Students

Emily Kuang, Selah Bellscheidt, Di Pham, Kristen Shinohara, Catherine Baker, Yasmine Elglaly

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2024. (In press)

[5] Enhancing UX Evaluation Through Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants: Effects of Proactive Dialogue and Timing

EMILY KUANG, MINGHAO LI, MINGMING FAN, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2024. (In press)

[6] Understanding Strategies and Challenges of Conducting Daily Data Analysis (DDA) Among Blind and Lowvision People

CHUTIAN JIANG, WENTAO LEI, EMILY KUANG, TENG HAN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 25th International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility, 2023, DOI: 10.1145/3597638.3608423

[7] Enhancing Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience Using the T9 Keyboard on Small Touchscreen Devices

EMILY KUANG, RUIHUAN CHEN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023, DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581105

[8] Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants for UX Evaluation: Questions and How to Ask them (Voice vs. Text)

Emily Kuang, Ehsan Jahangirzadeh Soure, Mingming Fan, Jian Zhao, Kristen Shinohara

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023, DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581247

[9] Bridging the Generational Gap: Exploring How Virtual Reality Supports Remote Communication Between Grandparents and Grandchildren

XIAOYING WEI, YIZHENG GU, EMILY KUANG, XIAN WANG, BEIYAN CAO, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023, DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581405

[10] "Merging Results Is No Easy Task": An International Survey Study of Collaborative Data Analysis Practices Among UX Practitioners

EMILY KUANG, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2022, DOI: 10.1145/3491102.3517647

# [11] "Too old to bank digitally?": A Survey of Banking Practices and Challenges Among Older Adults in China

XIAOFU JIN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference, 2021, DOI: 10.1145/3461778.3462127

#### [12] Compensated lens-free light field spectroscopy

AMENEH BOROOMAND, MOHAMMAD JAVAD SAHFIEE, LINDA WAND, EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG International Conference on Inverse Problems in Engineering, 2017

# JOURNAL ARTICLES

# [1] CoUX: Collaborative Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos for Digital Interfaces

EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (2021) pp. 1-11. 2021, DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114822. (First two authors contributed equally)

## [2] Compact, Field-Portable Lens-free Microscope using Superresolution Spatio-Spectral Light-field Fusion

FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, EMILY KUANG, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016). 2016, DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.105

# [3] Enhanced Smartphone Spectroscopy via High-throughput Computational Slit

EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016), 2016, DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.97

# PEER-REVIEWED EXTENDED ABSTRACTS & WORKSHOP PAPERS

# [1] Crafting Human-AI Collaborative Analysis for User Experience Evaluation

**EMILY KUANG** 

In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023, DOI: 10.1145/3544549.3577042

## [2] A Multi-scale Visual Analytics Approach for Exploring Biomedical Knowledge

FAHD HUSAIN, ROSA ROMERO-GÓMEZ, EMILY KUANG, DARIO SEGURA, ADAM CAROLLI, LAI CHUNG LIU, MANFRED CHEUNG, YOHANN PARIS Proceedings of the Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC), 2021, DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2109.06828. (Best Paper Winner)

# Honors and Awards

#### RECEIVED DURING PHD

- 2023 Google Ph.D. Fellowship in Human-Computer Interaction, Google
- 2022 AWARE-AI NRT Seed Funding Award (\$1000 USD), RIT
- 2022 Department Nomination for Microsoft Research Ph.D. Fellowship, RIT
- 2021 Best Paper Winner, Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC)
- Merit-based Ph.D. Scholarship, RIT 2020

# RECEIVED DURING UNDERGRADUATE

- 2018 Experience Award, Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC)
- 2018 President's Research Award, University of Waterloo
- 2017 President's Research Award, University of Waterloo
- **Undergraduate Student Research Award**, NSERC 2016
- 2015 **President's Scholarship of Distinction**, University of Waterloo

# **Invited Talks and Poster Presentations**

Nov 2023 Invited speaker, Youth Professional Career Development Series

Jan 2024 Invited panelist, AWARE-AI NRT Winter Retreat: Session on Resume Building and Internships

Remote

Apr 2023 Poster presenter, CHI Doctoral Consortium

Hamburg, Germany

Oct 2022 Poster presenter, RIT Artificial Intelligence Summit

Rochester, NY

Apr 2022 Poster presenter, CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women

New Orleans, LA

# Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

**ISTE-798 Future Interactions** 

<ul> <li>Collaborate with the course instructor to plan and organize course materials</li> <li>Mentor students and provide constructive feedback on assignments, projects, and research</li> </ul>		Juli 2024 - present
GUEST L	LECTURES	
Apr 2023	Crafting Human-AI Collaborative Analysis for UX Evaluation, PhD Research Colloquium (CISC896) Enhancing Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience, Design For Accessibility (ISTE266) Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos, Visual Analytics (ISTE782)	RIT RIT RIT
Servi	ce	
SERVICE	TO THE PROFESSION	
2023 2023 2023 2023 2022 2022 2021 2021	Associate Chair, Chinese CHI 2023 Reviewer: Technical Papers, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'24) Reviewer: Technical Papers, ACM Conference On Computer-Supported Cooperative Work And Social Computing (CSCW'23) Reviewer: Technical Papers, Frontiers in Computer Science (Sec. Human-Media Interaction) Reviewer: Technical Papers, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'23) Student Volunteer, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'22) Reviewer: Technical Papers, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'22) Student Volunteer, IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS'21) Reviewer: Late Breaking Work, Chinese CHI 2021	New Orleans, LA Remote
SERVICE	TO THE UNIVERSITY	
2023 2022	Trainee Council Representative, AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship Project Judge, Genius Olympiad	
Addit	ional Professional Experience	
North Inc. (now acquired by Google)		Kitchener, ON
	VISION DEVELOPER	Apr 2018 - Aug 2018
_	d algorithm to quantify image sharpness for multi-camera system assembly	T
Synaptive Medical Inc.  Optics Engineering Intern		Toronto, ON Sept 2017- Dec 2017
	ated the stabilization of stereoscopic videos for a neurosurgical robot	Jept 2011 - Dec 2011
	ael's Hospital	Toronto, ON
Medical Imaging Research Assistant		Jan 2017 - Apr 2017
Worked on a video processing pipeline for non-invasive detection of diabetic foot ulcers		

Rochester, NY